Welcome to the porch and thanks for tuning in. We're seeing God move
powerfully in our generation, throughout the country, and across the world. And
that's why this Labor Day weekend we're inviting any and every young adult here
to Dallas, Texas for AWAKEN, a national gathering hosted by us for you. If you
want to learn more, go to awaken.live. Now let's dive in.
Testing 1, 2, 3. Can you hear me? Well hey everyone and welcome to the porch. We're
going to be diving into the question that's been on everyone's mind. Why in
the world are women so hard to understand? I think what you meant to say
was why in the world are men so confusing? Okay, so it seems like both
genders may have some difficulty understanding each other. Which is why
each week we're spotlighting a different side of the room to dig into issues we
face within our own gender while growing an understanding for the opposite sex.
One night, we're putting the guys under the microscope. The next night is for the
girls. But don't worry, everybody's invited every night. Because here's the
thing we figured out. We're not actually short on opinions about men and women.
He's saying this. She's saying that. But what does God have to say about all of
it? Welcome to the debate that culture can't settle. Welcome to what's actually
true about him and about her. Welcome to your favorite Tuesday night series, He
Said, She Said. Well guys, first of all, you are welcome here. We are so glad you
are here. In fact, I think tonight is gonna make you a better boyfriend, a
better husband one day, a better son, a better brother. Tonight is going to help
you. I believe that this is a worthwhile investment for you. And while I'm going
to speak to the women, believe me there is plenty that is similar and there is
so much crossover to what we struggle with. I love, I need to start here, I love
being a girl. I love being a girl. Like, I'm in a very male-dominant world. Like, I
live in a world where many times I'm sharing the stage and I'm the only girl
there. Many times I'm at a table, I'm the only girl there. I'm in a very male
dominated world. But let me tell you, I love being a girl. I love watching
Gilmore Girls with my daughters. I love putting on high heels to be with you
tonight. I love getting my nails done. I am so glad I'm a girl. I love going up to
my husband and cuddling up and his arm getting around me. I love him opening the
door for me. I love him paying for things and taking care of me. I just like being
a girl, okay? I love it. And I need to start there because I think sometimes we're
really hard on our genders. We're really hard on our genders. And, and let me just
say, some of you just listened to what I said and you thought to yourself, "That
does not represent me at all." Like, I am a tomboy and I am proud of it and I do
not like it. And you know what? That is what makes this whole series so
dad-gum-heart. Because none of us can even agree on what it means to be a guy
or what it means to be a girl. And then I've heard, I've heard y'all been
debating about everything from should Jenny even be up on stage and I talking
in front of guys? And should, should there be, you know, women issues like porn more
dressed because they struggle with the same? I've heard that y'all have had
debate and wrestling and all these things. And let me just say, yes, because it is
not simple. You cannot define everything and put it all in a box, okay? So let me
just start there. Just start the night and say that I have been blessed to get
to listen to a lot of what Kylan has shared in the last few weeks. And let me
say this, last week he spoke to the men and I struggle with pride, I struggle
with anger, I struggle with lust, I struggle with all of these things, amen?
Like we are not necessarily siloed off into our corners struggling with our own
struggles. What it means to be in a girl's head though has been a mystery
for men for a long, long time. And so women, I want you to pull out your phone
and I want you to let the men into your head. Now guys, if you are sitting next to
a woman, I want you to close your eyes for a minute. Just take a little nap and
all the women, I want you to say, tonight we are talking about what women struggle
with. And so before I sit there and tell you what you struggle with, I thought it
just wise to start with you all having a voice and you tell us what you struggle
with, alright? So I'm gonna give you some prompts, here's a few, but I don't care
what you say. I want you to write in, I think about this all the time, I worry
about this, I fear this, I wish people knew this. This is what I struggle with.
So I want this to be personal, not what you think women struggle with, but what
you personally struggle with. So text it in to that number. Do y'all have the
number? You on it? Okay, they're gonna put up your answers live with your name. I'm
just kidding.
Just kidding.
[Silence]
I want you to yell out, as this is loading, what you typed in. Because some
poor guy is in the back typing as fast as he can.
Yell it out.
[Laughter]
[Silence]
Yeah.
Good.
[Silence]
How many women in here would say, "Comparison jealousy creeps in." Yeah.
As these keep filling the screen, I just want to hear from the men for a minute.
And when you hear those words and you look at the words on the screen, like, I
want to genuinely know, like, what do you feel? What? Heartbroken. Compassion. Say it
again. Relatable. Empathy. Who said hurt? Can you tell me why you said that really
loud?
[Silence]
Yeah.
So, these words, how many of you relate, guys, to a lot of these words? Yeah. So,
these words have given women a really bad rap. These words have made us feel like
we're too much, we're too emotional, we feel too big, we want too much, we're too
much in a room, we are isolating ourselves because we feel constantly like there is a
war in our head and we don't exactly know what to do with it. And I'm just going to
ask you to be very charismatic tonight, especially the women. If I say something
that is true that you relate to, will you just say, "Amen"? Because I'm going to be
real. I'm letting you in to some of the things that are in my head, and I am
trusting that I'm not alone. Amen? Thank you. So, together, we are going to work
through this as best we can, knowing that not one of us is the same. I cannot speak
on behalf of all women, which is why we had to start this way. I can just tell you
that I know what it's like to be up at 3 a.m. and have 8 million thoughts competing
for each other. I know what it feels like, even tonight, to wonder, before I get up
here, if I am enough, if I am a front. I know what it's like to fight a battle in
my head before I even got on stage to talk about a battle in your head. And we
think we're crazy, and guys, you think we're crazy, and let me just say that we
aren't crazy. We're under attack. There's an enemy, there's a scheme, there's a
strategy, there's a plan, and it is to shut down the church. And if he can't shut
down the whole thing, he'll shut down the half he can get to the best. And last
week, you know how he's coming after men. Well, guys, he's coming after women, too.
He's coming after women. 2 Corinthians 10, there's a war in our head, and we have
weapons that demolish strongholds. And until we recognize the war that is in
our heads, the fight that we are fighting, it is going to feel like we're so broken.
We're a pathology to be solved. We're diagnosis. Something is broken with me
rather than I am under attack and I need help. And guys, I want to speak to you
just for a minute. How you can listen to tonight is this. My husband is here on
the front row. He wasn't supposed to be here. He flew in from a business trip
early to get back and surprise me and was here. But let me just say that when he
walked in, when he walked in, my heart went from anxious to at ease. And I am not
saying that I need him to be here for me to obey God, for me to be bold, for me
to do what God's called me to do tonight. I'm just saying that he is my brother
in Christ and the man I sleep with. And it feels good. It feels good for him to
be here beside me. And guys, you may not be married yet. Many of you, most of you
are not. But you are a brother in Christ. And there is a way to support the women
in your life. And I want to pause and just, I want to speak to something that
Kylan brought up so boldly last week about pornography. The problem with
pornography for women, one, let me be clear. I get to hear the confessions of a
generation. I get to stand in the fronts of college campuses and of young adult
rooms all the time and I get to hear people confess to me. And there is the
same number of women confessing to me lust, masturbation, pornography as there
are men. So this is not siloed to men. So let me be clear because some of you may
wonder, like this message was about pornography to men. That is the struggle
of a generation. Why? Because we are so sexualized. Never has a generation
observed and seen more sexualized content on earth ever. And so all of our
minds have learned to view each other as sexual objects rather than brothers and
sisters in Christ. And let me just say though, specifically to men, the struggle
with porn and what it does to us as women is now instead of being our cheerleader,
instead of standing next to us and being able to support us and see us and help
us, all of a sudden we're objects to be used, consumed. That's the problem with
porn for us is you don't see us as a human with empathy, with compassion. Like
what the room just did. I'm going to tell you right now how many women's hearts
were so blessed just by hearing you yell out words like compassion, empathy. I
mean, women are like, "I needed to hear men say things like that." We need you to
do this. There's this word that I love in the Bible. It says, "Encourage each
other as long as it's called today, so that our hearts are not hardened by sin's
deceitfulness." The lost art of encouragement, men. Like you want to be a
great husband one day. You want to be a great brother in Christ right now. Learn
to encourage women. Not, very key, fix them. But encourage them. Because I'm
going to tell you how, even as before your boyfriend, before your husband,
before anything, I have a girl that I mentored this week that looked at me with
tears in her eyes and talked about her body image to me. She described how
insecure she was about a certain body part. I said, "Where did that come from
for you?" She said, "My guy friends were talking about that body part of mine.
I don't think they meant it as negative, but I haven't been able to get it out of
my head." And what a group of guy friends said to a girl in passing, laughing, not
thinking anything about it. Six months later, she's crying to her mentor about
it. Your words matter to us. And I'm going to give you another little piece of
wisdom. Just never talk about a girl's body. To them, behind their back, just
don't do it. Like, ever. Good or bad. Women, do we agree? All right. That just
helps us out. Because even if you're being positive, now all of a sudden, we
wonder what you mean. And we wonder if we're an object. And so just avoid it.
There's so many other things to notice. So many other things to notice. So this
is where I want to give you a vision of why this matters. If you've ever followed
me on Instagram, if you've ever seen me speak, you know that I have been blessed
to sit on the front row of Revival that is happening across the world. Not just
in the US, but all over the earth. I have seen it. It is happening, and it is just
getting started. And I believe, like many people, that we could be at endgame.
Like, I don't know, but we could be. And so let me tell you the cost of all of
these words in your head spinning, looping, over and over again, and the
cost of habits and addictions, men, where we don't co-labor together. We are
divided. We are consuming each other. We are defeated. We are discouraged. We don't
trust. We're not safe. And the mission of God is thwarted on earth because men and
women together, in the name of Jesus Christ, co-laboring, believing in each
other, encouraging each other, speaking life and truth over each other, seeing
the best in each other, that causes trouble to hell. It just does. It is so
rare. Do you realize how rare it is? And yet the Bible is full of it. People
co-laboring from Genesis on. You look at Genesis 1. It's Adam and Eve. He gives
them a mission from day one. Multiply. Be fruitful. Fill the earth. Care for the
earth. Be on mission together. Obey me. Surrender to me. Walk with me. Talk with
me. It was a co-laboring mission, and it wasn't one that was supposed to be
defined just by marriage. They just happened to be the first man and wife on
earth, so they were married. But this is not a story primarily about marriages or
families, although God uses that mightily. This is a story about all of the church
leaning in with all of their heart, with all of their gifts, not distracted by all
of these words, not distracted by all the addictions, and causing trouble as long
as we're here. That's where we're going. And God, that is, and I just want to say
this clearly, that is what is at stake. Like, that is the cost. I feel like so
much in my life, I use it to pull everybody back together, to remember that
this is not the point. It's just not the point. I'm going to tell you another
thing. Marriage, ending up with a ring on your finger, not the point. Great thing.
Not the main point. And so our minds are full of many, many things, and our minds,
I'm going to just say this, and again, this gets an amen if it's true, our minds
are really tired. And I pray that tonight, tonight, your mind gets to rest a little
bit. Here's what I know. Women can get a bad rap. And I'll say this, there are
plenty of women in scripture, it is fair. Eve was a bit of a troublemaker, and
there were plenty of others, and you end up in the New Testament, and you see
Paul, and he's calling us busybodies and gossips. So, you know, we have been
causing trouble for a long time. I am well aware. But this book, I just read it
in a month. In April, I read the Bible in a month, and that was an awesome
exercise. If you've never done that, you need to do that. It is so powerful.
You've done it. It is so good. It changed my life. It's so different than reading
scripture, because you just see it all, just boom, boom, boom. It's moving really
fast. And let me tell you what was a clear takeaway for me, is women were also
unbelievable in the Bible. There were so many heroes of women doing amazing
things in the Bible. You have Rahab, who risks her life because she believes in
the God of Israel. You have Esther, who risks her life because she wants the
welfare and the good of her people. You have Mary Magdalene pouring out, or no,
Mary Bethany pouring out perfume on Jesus' feet before he goes to the cross.
You have Mary Magdalene, who was with Jesus constantly in his ministry and
doing incredible works beside the disciples. And what you see is she's the
very first person that Jesus appears to when he comes back, and she goes and
tells everybody. She preaches the first gospel. You see Deborah, the judge and
prophetess that rides with confidence and strength and with grace. And this
book is a book about a lot of amazing women that have done amazing things for
God as well. And so I want to look at just one of them tonight. Mary, Jesus'
mother. She's a teenage girl in Nazareth. She's about to be asked to carry
something that she can't even imagine. But what she can imagine is she's a
teenage girl that is unmarried, and an angel shows up and tells her she's
pregnant. Luke 1, 28. "And he came to her and said, 'Greetings, O favored one.
The Lord is with you.' But she was greatly troubled at the saying and tried
to discern what sort of greeting this might be. And the angel said to her, 'Do
not be afraid, Mary, for you have found favor with God.'" Before God gives us an
assignment and a mission and a vision for the earth and using our gifts and
all the things that he wants to do to co-labor with us, God gives us his
presence. God wants us to know him. God wants us to know our identity with him.
And you look at Mary and she was afraid. I love that it says it. That she was
troubled. She's not sure about this. But the angel starts with, "I want you to
know you are God's favorite. He loves you. He likes you. He's with you. He's not
going anywhere." And, women, if we are going to fight the enemy that is coming
for us, that is trying to dismantle us, our lives, our thoughts, all of this, then
we have to begin with who we are in Christ. And when we believe that we have
the spirit of God inside of us, when we believe that God knows us and sees us
and walks with us in every single circumstance that we will walk with on
earth, something about that gives us strength and confidence and we are not
shut down anymore. And Mary was not shut down long. She was troubled.
She hadn't obeyed yet. She hadn't sacrificed anything yet. She hadn't
believed yet. But the angel said, "You're favored." She hadn't done the show.
She hadn't done the mighty work. And the angel said, "You're favored. I see you.
God sees you." Do you believe that? Because until you settle who you are
before God, the fear, the insecurity, all of it will consume you. But when you
know how he views you, it starts to shift. Luke 1, 34, "And Mary said to the
angel, 'How will this be since I'm a virgin?' And the angel answered her, 'The
Holy Spirit will come upon you, and the power of the Most High will overshadow
you, for nothing will be impossible with God.' And Mary said, 'Behold, I'm the
servant of the Lord. Let it be to me according to your word.'" Now, I want to
address one of the things I saw up there a lot. As women who long to be married,
which is a beautiful and good desire if that is you, we have very little control
in this story. And it is paralyzing and can feel helpless and hopeless. And I
have walked with dozens and dozens of my sisters in Christ who have wrestled with
that feeling. And I want to say this very clearly, whether it is that you are
longing for a boyfriend, for a husband, whether it is that you are longing for
more security in your life, whether it is you are longing for respite from the
mind that has tormented you, whatever it is that you are longing for, one of my
favorite lines in this book I just read to you, Mary says to God, "Let it be as
you say." She has no idea she's going to watch that baby die. She has no idea what
it is going to feel like when people find out she's pregnant and not married.
She has no idea the pain and the suffering that she is going to have to walk
through. She just says, "Your will, not mine. Amen." I don't know what it is like
to be 35 and single. I don't know. But I do know what it is like to suffer, to
suffer in ways I can't share on stages or on Instagram or anywhere because it's
not mine to share. But I know what it is like to long for something about my
circumstances to change. And I can tell you that those words are the scariest
freaking words you can pray. Not my will, but your will. Let it be whatever you
say, God. But I'll tell you a secret. Every time I repray this prayer, seek ye
first the kingdom of God, and somehow all these other things get added to me, and
somehow all these other things get healed, and somehow as I lay down my life,
there is this freedom and this peace that comes even though none of my
freaking circumstances changed. And I wish, and I prayed, and I've asked, and I've
begged, and they don't change. And yet, somehow there is a supernatural peace
that floods my soul, my mind, my life, my relationships because I just say, "Let it
be as you say, God." I just, I can't control it, and I'm done trying.
When we say it, when we say it, things do not magically happen. The guy does not
get down on the knee. He doesn't ride in in a white horse. The baby doesn't
come right away. Like, it doesn't get fixed right away, but I can tell you
that's not the point. That's not our point. We exist for purposes beyond what we
imagine on a given Tuesday. And so Mary knows it. Little teenage girl has some
grasp, some grasp that there is something bigger happening than her comfort,
something bigger happening than her circumstances, something bigger
happening than her reputation. And she says this, "And in those days, Mary
rose and went with haste into the hill country, and Elizabeth was filled with
the Holy Spirit, her cousin, and exclaimed with a loud cry, 'Blessed are
you among women, and blessed is the fruit of your womb. Blessed is she who
believed that she would be a fulfillment for what was spoken to her from the
Lord.'" At that point that we know of, Elizabeth is the first person that Mary
goes and sees. And I want you to think about your life, and I want you to think
about the things that you shared or the things you didn't, that you wouldn't
type, that you need to share. The fears, the worries, the overwhelm that you
regularly are fighting on a given 2 a.m. night, I want you to think about those
things, and I want you to think, "Am I a girl? Am I a guy who runs to tell
someone?" I've done all this therapy, and let me save you all the money.
You can't live in your head by yourself. You can't work it out by yourself.
You can't solve it by yourself. You can't get well by yourself. You can't get
healed by yourself. You can't get whole by yourself. You can't find what you're
looking for by yourself. Mary knew she needed a friend. So cute. It's really
darling. Like, she just finds out she is impregnated with God, and she's like,
"I'm going to go see my cousin, you know? I'm going to go pregnant and see my
cousin." And she gets to her cousin, and her cousin's like, "Let's have a party.
This is unbelievable." And there's a perspective I know that she gets just
because she's with Elizabeth. I can't wait to get to heaven and talk to Mary.
When I get there, I'm going to be like, "Were you afraid? Were you filled with
faith? Did caring God make you just crazy full of faith? I bet you she was a
little bit anxious and a little bit worried and a little bit fearful about
what was about to happen. I'm just banking that she was still human." And
then she goes all the way to her cousin, and her cousin gives her what? Her
cousin gives her perspective. Her cousin gives her hope. Her cousin gives her a
vision. Her cousin gives her a way of thinking about the world and the
situation that she needed. Her cousin gave her encouragement. Her cousin spoke
life over her. Let me just tell you, if your mind, if you feel in bondage in your
mind and you have never shared it out loud, there is a reason that you have not
started to get free. I watch it all the time, these college kids. They yell out
their sin. It's unbelievable, and it's, I mean, it's brazen sin, you know, and
they're just yelling it out. "Abortion!" from the back of the room. "Abortion!"
And the room breaks. They break. Something begins to heal when we say it out
loud to our brothers and to our sisters. And last, Luke 1, 46, 49, "And Mary said,
'My soul magnifies the Lord, and my spirit rejoices in God my Savior, for he
has looked on the humble estate of his servant. For behold, from now on, all
generations will call me blessed, for he who is mighty has done great things for
me, and holy is his name.'" She magnifies the Lord. What are you magnifying?
What are you magnifying? Because what you magnify, what you make great in your
life, what you care about most, the scrapbook you build that you need to have
accomplished by the time you're 30, whatever it is that you magnify, that is
what your life is becoming. You can't aim at one thing and hit another. You aim at
one thing, you hit that thing. You aim at getting rich. You aim at getting the
husband or the wife. You aim at getting the respect of everybody. You aim at
getting everybody to like you. You aim at control. You aim at the body. You aim at
fixing everything about yourself. You aim at making sure you look good. You will
hit that, maybe. And that is why this is a central message to your soul. This isn't
about men and women. This is about God and you. This is about an enemy that
hates you. This really isn't he said, she said. This is he said the devil, he said
God. That's the war for all of us. Because the enemy is talking and we're not
really talking back. We're letting him tell us whatever he wants to say and
we've let our lives be defined by it and we're completely shut down. And so we're
afraid. We're numb. We have self-doubt and we think it's a diagnosis and so we
take a drug. We are fans of the counseling world. We are fans of doctors
and medicine when needed. But church, we are also fighting demonic realms. We are
also fighting dark cosmic forces that hate us. We are fighting an enemy that
John 844 says is a liar. He says it five different times, five different ways in
the same sentence so that we will know there is an enemy. He hates us and the
way he's gonna get to us is he's gonna lie to us. And so he will make you swing
for the wrong fences all life long. And there's a war. And we're living for
things that look good and sound good but never fill our soul. Because let me just
tell you, those of you that think your soul will be filled when you find the
man, let me tell you what. I don't always feel the way I did about him today.
Because if I don't fill my soul with God and I look to Zach Allen to fill my soul,
I will kill our marriage. So get this right now. She's not gonna fix it. He's
not gonna fill it. Your porn addiction isn't gonna go away when you get married.
Do the business today that God is calling you to do today. Magnify the Lord. Set
your heart and your mind on the mission and the glory of God on earth. And I'm
telling you, it goes well with you. Somebody asked me the other day, their
ministry was not thriving and they were feeling like it should be bigger and
they were asking me like, "How do I deal with this? I want it to be bigger. I
think it should be bigger." And I looked at him and I was like, "What games are
we playing, man?" He was like, "That's easy for you to say. You're leading this
big thing." And I was like, "Whoa, if I cared that I was leading a big thing, my
soul could never lead the thing." Like we got to deal with this stuff before we
have the responsibility. You got to get free before you are in the family
managing it. You've got to get free now. I have these men in my life. I want to
paint a picture for you guys. JP, a lot of y'all know him. JP is one of my
dearest friends. We have been together a long time. And we've been on the road
together ministering beside each other. He pastored me when we were at Watermark
years ago. And that man, all the time this happens. All the time. People say to
me, "Man, JP was talking about you the other day. Man, he respects you. Man, he
likes you. Man, he's proud of you." That happens to me all the time. And that man
and I, I mean, we're in rooms. He's deferred. He's going, "What do you think?
What do you think?" We are co-laboring for Jesus on earth that revival would come
and that souls will be saved. And we're not really stopping and thinking about
like, "Oh, wow. I don't want to offend you. I don't want to offend you. You're a
boy. I'm a girl." We're just running our guts out as fast as we can. And he
believes in me and he speaks well of me. I've got another man here. His name is
Timothy Atik. That man is my pastor. And can you imagine being an elder and a
pastor of a girl like me? Like, this is a lot. And they've never acted like it.
The elders and TA have been like, "Jenny, we are for you. We are behind you.
Whatever God is calling you to do, we believe in you." I have submitted. I want
you to know as a woman, I believe the scriptures that say submission. Submission
has gone well for me. Submitting to them has been a protection in my life.
Submitting to my husband has been a protection in my life. You know why?
Because one day we're going to get to heaven and God's going to say, "Hey, you
did that wrong." And I was like, "Well, Zach and the elders said I could do it."
Love submission. Then I have this other man, Zach Allen. Y'all, let me just show
the pictures of what this man does when I am speaking. When I am on the stage,
what he is, he is backstage always crying. Crying like a baby. He's already crying.
I can see it. His eyes are glistening down here. And praying for me. And you
know what he does? The reason I feel less anxious when he walks in the room is
because he's my biggest fan. He sits down right beside me, he prays over me, and
he's like, "Go have fun, baby." I mean, you talk about a sexy man. Like, that is
a sexy man. Showing up for me. You know why he does that? Because he truly
believes that whatever is best for the kingdom of God is best for us. And if
putting me on a stage, on a plane, wherever, and he, you know, might have to
do this sometimes, he is like, "Go, baby girl, because we are in this for those
fences, not the world. We're in it for the kingdom." And so we are colaboring.
And sometimes that man gets on stage and it's everybody's favorite. He's like my
most listened to podcast. Like, everybody wants him on stage. But that man often
is saying, "Jenny, you need to do this thing that scares you. You need to obey
God." That is a man of God. Amen. I'm going to close with this. I'm going to
close with this. And as I do, the band's going to come out. And here's what I
want to happen, guys. Let's do business tonight. Okay? Let's do business. Like,
what is the thing that you need to say no more? I'm not giving my thought life to
that thing anymore. Because 2 Corinthians 10 tells us that we can take every
thought captive. So we don't have to be a slave to our body image anymore. We
don't have to. We don't have to give our mind to small things. My daughter this
week, she was home alone and she called us and said, we were together, a lot of
people in our family, and she said, "Mom, I'm scared. I hear these noises and I've
been watching these murder shows. And I want you all to come home. Like, come
home." And I turned to her older brother and I said, "This is what happened." And
he goes, "Caroline, play silly games, get silly prizes." We've been playing silly
games and getting silly prizes. We've been giving our lives and setting our
minds on things and then we're afraid and we're so surprised. So we stop playing
the game. We just say no more and that is the business tonight I want us to do. We
spit in the enemy's face. We don't just let him speak to us. We don't let him
just play the game. We say no more. I'm going to honor women in my life. If
there's one thing men say about you, let it be that you honor women. It's a great
thing. That goes a long way. In every way, in private, in public. And women, let it
be said of us that we didn't play silly games. That we didn't give our mind, our
thoughts, our words, our time, our energy to silly games to win silly prizes.
Because there is an enemy. And if I were him, if I were your enemy, I would use
whatever works to shut you down. To her, I'd start the loop. You're behind. You're
too much. You're not enough. You're too sensitive. You're too harsh. You should
have texted back sooner. You shouldn't have texted back at all. Everyone's
getting married. Everyone's getting promoted. Everyone's fine without you.
Fix your face. Don't eat. You shouldn't have eaten that. Work out. Work out. Work
out. Did they mean something by that? They meant something by that. You're being
dramatic. Pray about it. You should be past this now. You're still not past this.
I wouldn't need to say any of this twice. I'd just leave the loop running and go to
work on him. To him, I wouldn't start with a thought. I'd start with a habit. A tab
open too long. A scroll that doesn't end. A drink that becomes too, becomes normal.
I'd give him a screen to disappear into instead of a room of community to walk
into. I'd let him call it stress relief. I'd let him call it just how guys are. I'd
let porn do quietly what shame does loudly. Teach him a woman is something to
consume, not something to labor beside. I'd let his silence pass as strength. I'd
let his anger pass as passion. I'd let him go a whole year without one friend who
actually knows what he's carrying and let him think that just, that's what a man
does. That's what it costs. And don't think I only work one way. That would be
lazy and I'm not lazy. Some of you men lie awake, running, her exact same loop,
afraid, behind, not enough, still not past it. You just haven't said it out loud.
And some of you women are exactly as hooked as he is, just quieter, better at
the same tab, the same shame. It's doing its work. It's doing it quietly. And I
don't care which sin you go for. I don't care what gender you are. I only care
that it works. Her mind, a war she's fighting, alone in a crowd, his life, a
war he's not fighting at all. I'd let her mistake his numbness for not caring. I'd
let him mistake her spinning for too emotional. I'd let them walk past each
other a thousand times, both convinced the other one was the problem. Neither one
realizing they'd both already lost to me before they even spoke. That's the real
win. Not just her alone. Not just him alone. A whole generation of men and
women, each fighting a private war, too depleted to ever fight side by side. An
entire room like that? Missing the call of God in their life? What if an entire
room was free, awake, done being afraid of each other, turning outward instead of
inward, turned a mission bigger than either of them. Men and women wholly,
completely surrendered to God. That is the one thing I have never figured out
to stop, so I'll keep doing what's worked. Her loop, his habit, your loneliness in a
room this full, small things, quiet things, things you would never call spiritual
warfare because they just look like a normal Tuesday. We're in the middle of it.
We're in the middle of it. He hates us. I think it's endgame. I think the Avengers
need to get in the game. I think we need to care enough to fight back against
these things that have consumed us for too long. And compassion grows, and
empathy grows, and understanding grows. I mean, I love the verses. You want to know
what makes a great man? My husband, he lives with me in an understanding way,
Scripture says. Peter wrote, "Live with your wives in an understanding way," and
he lays down his life as Christ laid down his life for the church. That is what it
means to be a good man, to honor women. Live with us in an understanding way. I
know right now it may not be your wife. It's probably your sister in Christ, but
live with her in an understanding way. Be curious. Be angry that she is getting
beat up because it may not be. It likely isn't physical, but spiritually she's
getting beat up, guys. Pray for her. Fight for her. And women, tonight is really for
you. Like, we are going to open the altar, and the band is going to play, and what I
want you to do tonight, I want you to come down, and I want you to, I mean, this is
so old school camp, you ready? I want you to leave it here. Like, what is the thing
you put up there and say, "I don't want to obsess about this anymore. I don't want
to be addicted to this anymore. I don't want to think about this anymore." And I
also, throughout the entire room, and in the overflow room as well, in fact, you
guys feel free to come in here. Come in here, fill the aisles, just wherever you
are, in the chapel, come on. And what I would say, fire hazards, okay, I don't
know what's going to happen, but just come on. It'll be fine, they tell me. But
what I know, what I know is that we need to be sharing with each other what it is.
You don't need to just text it in. You need to say it to a friend. You need to
say it out loud to somebody. So all over the room, what I want to happen is you're
coming forward, you're surrendering it to God, and you're saying it out loud to
someone. And you're praying for each other. Because we are fighting spiritual
forces. And guess the greatest weapon we have against the spiritual forces? It is
to pray. They cannot stand against surrender, against prayer, against a
people wholly and completely surrendered to God. So we surrender. We lay it down.
Whatever you need to do to do business tonight, to get in the game, because it
matters. So God, I bless this room. In fact, right now, God, I pray that you
would reveal to every single person that can hear my voice, whether it's through
the camera in their living room, whether it's in the overflow room, whether it's
up in the back of the balcony, in the very back on the back row, I pray right
now that every single heart would feel conviction rising up in them from your
Holy Spirit. And God, you know what each person needs to feel, what each person
needs to confess, what each person needs to lay down. Only you can show that. And
God, I pray if it is the thing they are afraid to do, would tonight be the night
they do it. God, I pray that if it is the shadow, dark thing that they're afraid to
say out loud, would tonight be the night they say it. God, we don't want to miss
all the good works that you prepared in advance for us to do. We want to run our
races, co-laboring, not stuck, but free. Show us how to get there. In Jesus' name.
Amen.